A Finding Aid to the Robert Perine Research Material on the Chouinard Art Institute, circa 1923-circa 1985, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Robert Perine research material on the Chouinard Art Institute
circa 1923-circa 1985
Archives of American Art
Perine, Robert
AAA.perirobe
Archival Resource Key
1.8 Linear feet
The Robert Perine research material on the Chouinard Art Institute measures 1.8 linear feet and date from circa 1923 to circa 1985. Documents consist of research material used in Perine's book Chouinard: An Art Vision Betrayed (1985) including catalogs for the Chouinard Institute and California Institute of the Arts; notes and preliminary writings for the book, including an annotated table of contents and a bibliography; floor plans of the Institute; material concerning the lawsuit brought against the board of trustees in an attempt to prevent the closing of the school; 158 photographs of Nelbert Chouinard, classes, students and buildings; and 27 sound cassettes of interviews of 52 artists and staff, some with partial transcripts.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Biographical / Historical
Painter, educator, and author Robert Perine (1922-2004), was a student and later a professor at the Chouinard Art Institute. The Chouinard Art Institute was founded in Los Angeles, California, by Ms. Nelbert M. Chouinard in 1921. The Institute received financial support from Walt Disney who also oversaw its merger with the Los Angeles Conservatory of Music to form the Californian Institute of the Arts in 1961. The Chouinard Art Institute continued to operate as its own entity within the California Institute of the Arts until it was completely absorbed by the California Institute of the Arts in 1972.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as four series.
Series 1: Writings, 1930, 1962, circa 1980-circa 1985 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Printed Material, 1931-1984 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Photographs, circa 1923-1977 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Interviews, circa 1979 (0.9 linear feet; Box 1-3)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The research material was donated to the Archives of American Art by Robert Perine in 1987.
Scope and Contents
The Robert Perine research material on the Chouinard Art Institute measures 1.8 linear feet and date from circa 1923 to circa 1985. Documents consist of research material used in Perine's book Chouinard: An Art Vision Betrayed (1985) including catalogs for the Chouinard Institute and California Institute of the Arts; notes and preliminary writings for the book, including an annotated table of contents and a bibliography; floor plans of the Institute; material concerning the lawsuit brought against the board of trustees in an attempt to prevent the closing of the school; 158 photographs of Nelbert Chouinard, classes, students and buildings; and 27 sound cassettes of interviews of 52 artists and staff, some with partial transcripts.
Existence and Location of Copies
Some of the sound recordings in this collection have been copied for research access and are available in the Archives of American Art offices.
Chouinard Art Institute (Los Angeles, Calif.); California Institute of the Arts; Educators -- California -- Los Angeles; Sound recordings; Interviews; Painters -- California -- Los Angeles; Authors -- California -- Los Angeles; Art -- Study and teaching -- California -- Los Angeles; Chouinard, Nelbert, 1879-1967; Chouinard Art Institute (Los Angeles, Calif.)
- Writings, 1930; 1962; circa 1980-circa 1985; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Material includes footnotes, an annotated table of contents, quotes, and other notes related to Perine's book Chouinard: An Art Vision Betrayed. Also included is Perine's resume.
  - "Chouinard: The Mother, The Children, the Art" Annotated Table of Contents, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Draft Notes, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Draft Notes, Footnotes, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Draft Notes, Quotes, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Draft Notes, Usable Quotes, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Draft Notes, References, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Echoes of the Madame and Her School", circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Floor Plans, 1930, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Draft Notes, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Resume, circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Printed Material, 1931-1984; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Printed material includes academic catalogs for both the Chouinard Art Institute and the California Institute of the Arts, newsletter from the Californian Institute of the Arts, newspaper and magazine clipping related to the Chouinard Institute, and copies of legal documents related to the Chouinard Art Institute. The series is arranged chronologically.
  - Chouinard Art Institute Faculty and Classes, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chouinard Art Institute Catalogs, 1937-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chouinard Art Institute Catalogs, 1941-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Existence and Location of Copies
    The entirety of the catalogue marked 1945-1946 has not been scanned because it is an exact duplicate of the catalogue marked 1941-1942.
  - Chouinard Art Institute Catalogs, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rite of Spring, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - California Institute of the Arts Catalogs, 1963-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
  - California Institute of the Arts Alumni Association, 1966-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - California Institute of the Arts, "The Concept', undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - California Institute of the Arts Newsletters, 1965-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23-27)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1968-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Chouinard Legal Documents, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Photographs, circa 1923-1977; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Photographs document student life, artwork, faculty, and school grounds at the Chouinard Art Institute.
  - Chouinard Art Institute, circa 1923-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31-38)
- Interviews, circa 1979; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Found here are interviews Perine conducted with staff of the Chouinard Art Institute for use in his book. There are partial transcripts for some of the interviews. The series is arranged with the transcripts first in alphabetical order followed by the audio cassettes. Since there are multiple interviews on each cassette, the cassettes are in no particular order.
  - Partial Transcripts, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39-41)
    Partial transcripts exist for the following interviews: Rex Brandt, Mrs. Chouinard, Watson Cross, Marc Davis, Harry Diamond, Phil Dike and Sheets, Haines, Hauser, Alex Hovsepian, Bill Moore and James Normile, Phil Paradise, Rubin, Mary Vartikian, and Elin Waite.
  - Interviews, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key; 17 Sound cassettes (Box 2)
    Interviews include the following individuals: Huebner, David Thorne, Elmer Plummer, Mrs. Brugger, Brandt, Monohan, M. Clark, James Normile, Sheets, Watson Cross, Hauser, Ed Reep, Mary Vartikian, Haines, Millie Rocque, Ruth Hatfield, Mary Nystrom, Marjory Best, Mrs. Belzer, F. Diamond, Edith Head, Davis, Alex Hovsepian, Bob Mackie, Ned Jacoby, Bob Irwin, Bob, Mason, Corinne Hartley, Lou Danziger, and Rubin.
  - Interviews, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key; 11 Sound cassettes (Box 3)
    Interviews include the following: Phil Paradise, V. Partch and George Giroux, D. Constable, La Doriva, Herb Jepson, Ted Gibson, Jim Real, Wal Batterton, Roysher, Geo Hall, Katherine Hall, Mary Lea, Shiela de Bretteville, Wing Fong, Lee Blair, Woelffer, Clay Walker, Lalla Lezli, Cleo Dorman, Sheets, Janice Garbuit, Eva Roberts, Lee Blair, Pauline Annon, Alice Davis, Mary Nystrom, McMillan, Betty Armstrong, Fred Gardner, Rogers, Pokey Baker, Ruth Hatfield, Romero, Harry and fran Diamond, Cross, Marv Rubin, Elin Waite, Dave Smith, Trout, Gabrielson, and Mrs. Chouinard.